So, let me discuss one more
example, or just go through a few
more cases on the example
just seen on the slides.
I had already mentioned things that
were not visible on the slide.
For example, that it is quite possible that
there is more than one token in one place.
And then one can also ask oneself
what happens, for example, during firing.
Let's take a look at this situation.
This would be our starting position for the Petri
net with the same structure as on the slides.
But the initial situation would be that we
would have two tokens here on the left place.
What is the case then in terms of firing?
It is still the case that these
three transitions cannot fire at the beginning.
This transition is still allowed to
fire, because the requirement is that
it must have at least one
token on each of its incoming arrows.
So the fact that there are
two tokens here doesn't detract from that.
The transition can still fire.
What happens then?
Then a corresponding number of
tokens are taken from the places.
So one token from here and actually
only one of the two tokens here.
Then the transition would fire and would put
a token on each of its postcondition places.
So you could imagine it like this.
And afterwards, this one
token is still up here.
So the firing of the transition
doesn't have to empty one place.
Simply as many tokens are
consumed as the input arrows require.
Therefore in this case
the postcondition would be fulfilled.
We would now have put down these two
tokens and that would be the new condition.
How could we continue then?
Then, for example, each of
these three transitions could fire next.
For example, we could fire this
transition first, as we did before.
Then we would get into the situation
that there are two tokens up here.
And if, for example, we were
to fire this transition again afterwards, we
would be back in the starting situation.
It is just as conceivable that, for
example, tokens already lie on the post-condition places.
This could also have
been our initial assignment.
And also then we are
allowed to fire this transition.
So that says, it must
be consumed along the input arrows
and generated along the output arrows.
And that doesn't take away from the
fact that there's already a token here.
It is not the case that
the space here is occupied and
therefore the transition should not be fired.
The fact that there is
already a token is not detrimental.
In the situation as it is
shown here now, these transitions could fire.
Of course, these two transitions could
also fire, because of this token.
But let's assume that
we fire this middle transition.
Then this would mean of course:
A corresponding number of tokens are
taken from the input, like this,
then placed on the output positions,
and it would look like this.
Then two tokens will end up here.
One token because it was already
there before firing, and one token
because it was added from here.
This is also allowed.
The transitions do not have to find empty
places in their postcondition places.
They may be already occupied.
Then they will be even fuller afterwards.
Then we would have an
interesting situation here in this case,
insofar as now these
two transitions are both activated.
We had said earlier (in
the example on the slide)
that these two
transitions were in conflict.
Because we had a token here.
And then once we had decided
to put this one down here.
And then the system was dead because the token
had been removed from the system and was no longer
available to fire this
transition again later, for example.
Now it would be like this:
If there are two tokens on the spot,
then there is no more
problem between these two transitions.
Now, for example, the lower transition
could fire and take this token,
and the upper transition could
fire and take this token.
Then both of them
would have been possible.
And even though we have taken
this one token out of the
system, the system
is not necessarily dead.
Because, for example, it could
continue to operate and fire accordingly
now with the upper token present.
So quite different cases
that can occur here.
In that case, sure:
If I would now decide
to go down with the token,
then the system would be
dead again sooner or later.
Because then, at most,
these paths would still
be possible, and then this
transition would indeed fire again.
But for example up to here the
system was not in this dead end.
If I decide here to
go up again instead, I can
just also progress further in
the processes of the system.
These were a few constellations
that I wanted to discuss.
And then I had already mentioned on
the slides that it could also be that
at these arrows here (which we have
everywhere) there is still the information that
not necessarily when firing it always has
to be about exactly one token per position.
Let's consider a situation where I remove these two
tokens so that I have the same starting situation
as at the very beginning, but for example
there would be a 2 at this arrow here.
This then means that
when this transition fires,
and it has taken appropriate
tokens from the precondition places, it
will of course still deposit
tokens in its postcondition places.
But because of the 2 here, firing
this transition would always deposit two tokens.
So firing here would mean:
Consume token, consume token, drop
token here, drop two tokens here.
That also means that you can't
think of it as the tokens that
were up here before somehow being
preserved and moving through the system.
It may look like that if there were two
tokens before and afterwards there are two tokens again.
But for example, in the case where we had
one token on each upper place before and afterwards, because of
these 2 here at the bottom left, there are now two tokens, then
it looks as if a new token has been created.
But in reality it is always like that:
Tokens are always consumed
and tokens are always created.
One must not assume that the number of
tokens in the system
must somehow always remain constant.
That's more by chance when
each transition has as many
incoming as outgoing arrows, and there's
never an annotation like this anywhere here.
Then it is so.
It is also so if there were three incoming
arrows here and two outgoing arrows, whose sum is 3.
In the case with the 2
here the following processes are possible:
Then actually in the case the number
of tokens in the system will increase in
total with each
firing of this transition.
Now we would again consume one token
from here, consume one token from here,
put down one token here,
put down two tokens here.
Then we would have
unlimited resource creation because
every time this transition fires, a
token is put into the system.
It would be different, for example, if
there was a 2 here as well.
Because then that means
that every time this transition
fires, two tokens have to
be taken from the left place.
So then it could go on like
this, starting from the situation (assuming we
had reached that somehow), that, for example,
in the situation now this transition could
not fire (because it finds one token here,
but there would be no two tokens here).
Then it would be necessary to
add another token to the upper left.
This could be for example this
one after firing the leftmost transition.
And what would happen now?
Now this transition could fire.
It could also fire, for example, after
we have moved this token up here.
And firing now would mean taking one token
from the right, taking two tokens from the left,
giving one token to the right
and giving two tokens to the left.
So firing here now would mean:
We have to consume one token from here,
we have to consume two tokens from here,
we have to put one token
here and put two tokens here.
And then, of course, we can get
into a situation where actually the system
becomes dead-locked because of that, because
we take tokens away from the system.
Let's say we have this 2
up here, but no 2 down here,
but just a normal simple
arrow with no such label.
What would happen then?
Then, for example, such transitions
would still be possible here.
Then now, to fire this transition, one
token would have to be taken from
the right, two tokens from the left.
But in the output, there would only
be one token here, one token here.
Because nowhere here is
a number greater than 1.
That is, then a
possible sequence would be:
Here this token disappears, these
two tokens disappear, on the
right a token is added, on the
left also only one token is added.
And then we have seen
that in that step the total
number of tokens in
the system has just decreased.
And then sooner or later that would lead to
the fact that we don't have enough tokens anymore.
So we could fire
again here, fire again here.
Then we could fire this transition again.
That would result in
these three tokens disappearing,
and one token would appear
in each post-condition location.
So then we would be here.
But in total, there would only
be three tokens left in the system.
And then we could still fire
here, fire here, fire here for example.
And then we wouldn't be able to continue
because this transition would never be able to fire.
Because it would never find
two tokens on the left.
The fact that there are two
tokens here on the right doesn't help.
Because the 2 is at
this left entrance of the transition.
There are many different options, but
they are all based on
this simple concept of firing.
A transition must find enough
tokens on its precondition places.
Sufficient tokens means one
token per position, unless there
are such numerical labels on them.
Then there must be at
least a corresponding number of tokens.
If there are more, then only
as many are consumed as are needed.
If the transition can fire, afterwards
on the postcondition places
accordingly many tokens are put.
At least one per arrow.
If there are any numbers on
them, there will be more than one.
And if there were already tokens on the
positions, the positions were not
empty, then something is added.
These are all cases
that we have already discussed.